<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rodrigo Araújo</title>
    <description>Stories and thoughts on Computer Science</description>
    <link>http://digorithm.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://digorithm.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on Visualizing Software Architecture</title>
        <description>
          
          The more I think about the advantages and disadvantages of upfront design, the more I find it a really complex subject, I mean, the whole Software architecture diagramming in general. I’ve been following the development of the C4 model for a considerable time, I find it interesting, but it still...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/thoughts-visualizing-software-arch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/thoughts-visualizing-software-arch</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neural Computation: Toward an Intuitive Understanding of the Perceptron</title>
        <description>
          
          Artificial Neurons is one of the most beautiful ways to simulate a biological behavior through computation, despite the fact that it’s not very close to the level of details of a real neuron. But it captured the core of what a neuron is doing. And I find that trying to...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/neural-computation-pt1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/neural-computation-pt1</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Case Study: Sentiment Analysis On Movie Reviews</title>
        <description>
          
          Well, this case was a fun one, sentiment analysis is a sub type of NLP (natural language processing) in which you have to train a model to analyze a text, and classify it was a negative sentiment or a positive sentiment. In this case, I wanted to apply it on...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/case-study-sentiment-analysis-movie-reviews</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/case-study-sentiment-analysis-movie-reviews</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Generic Architecture for Text Classification with Machine Learning</title>
        <description>
          
          One of the most commons tasks in Machine Learning is text classification, which is simply teaching your machine how to read and interpret a text and predict what kind of text it is. The purpose of this essay is to talk about a simple and generic enough Architecture to a...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/generic-architecture-text-classification</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/generic-architecture-text-classification</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Case Study: Python Performance on rotating one-dimensional vectors</title>
        <description>
          
          I’m a big fan of a nice challenge, therefore, I like books like Programming Pearls, I like to dive into many kinds of solutions to the same problem and try to differentiate them by novelty, performance, elegance, etc… This time I was playing with a fun problem, from the column...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/case-study-python-performance-rotating-vector</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/case-study-python-performance-rotating-vector</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web Scaling - using Redis as Cache</title>
        <description>
          
          Redis is such a great technology. Unfortunately, there’s still people who don’t know Redis or don’t know that Redis can be used as a Cache System to improve the speed of responses. Why Redis Well, let’s start this discussion remembering how a common Relational Database basically works: Suppose we’re using...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/web-scaling-using-redis-as-cache</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/web-scaling-using-redis-as-cache</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building your first REST API with Python</title>
        <description>
          
          Are you total lost in this world full of jargons like: API, Rest API, microservices and stuffs? Come here, sit, grab a cup of coffee, and let’s talk briefly about it. Today a lot is said about APIs. Everything has an API, every programmer (newbie to expert) uses tons of...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/build-your-first-rest-api-python</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/build-your-first-rest-api-python</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using Python and AI to predict types of wine</title>
        <description>
          
          I’ve been working with AI/Machine Learning at Jusbrasil recently, and it’s being pretty challenging due to the huge amount of data that we have to deal with, so cleaning this data and making predictions and classifications in an acceptable time demands a nice AI architecture. That said I can say...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/using-python-and-ai-to-predict-wine</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/using-python-and-ai-to-predict-wine</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making your machine think, learn and predict - Gradient Descent Algorithm in Java</title>
        <description>
          
          How can we make a machine learn from data? Then, how can we make the machine predicts things based on that learned data? Those are the question answered by one of the most classic Machine Learning Algorithms, the Gradient Descent Algorithm, from a Mathematical-Statistical side it’s called Univariate Linear Regression....
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/2015-01-09-Making-Your-Machine-Think-Learn-And-Predict-Gradient-Descent-Algorithm-in-Java/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/2015-01-09-Making-Your-Machine-Think-Learn-And-Predict-Gradient-Descent-Algorithm-in-Java/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why, how and where to Learn Design Patterns</title>
        <description>
          
          The first thought I had when I started to study Design Patterns was: - “damn, is all this really necessary?” I mean, so many patterns, so many details to do things that look simple to do without any further detailed thoughts. And I started to question myself if this was...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/learn-design-patterns</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/learn-design-patterns</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on Automata Theory</title>
        <description>
          
          I’ve been reading many texts on automata theory these times, and let me tell you, that’s such a wonderful thing. It pretty much explain how computers can…. compute! Simply put, Automata Theory deals with the logic of computation with respect to simple machines, referred to as Automata. From the mathematical...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/thoughts-on-automata-theory</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/thoughts-on-automata-theory</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fun with graphs pt1</title>
        <description>
          
          Graph Theory is definitely one of my favorite branches of the Mathematics &amp;amp; Computer Science, mostly because of its nearest infinity applications, in both real world problems and pure theoretical problems. These days I’ve been working (with my buddy Daniel Almeida) in a framework to create and manipulate graphs. Which...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/fun-with-graphs-pt1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/fun-with-graphs-pt1</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CRUD with Java, JSP and MySQL</title>
        <description>
          
          One of the most common kind of applications in today&#39;s tech/business world is the CRUD system, that is the idea of the user interacting with a database, so the user can Create, Retrieve, Update and Delete (yep, that awful name came from this) data from this database. Also, learning how...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/crud-with-java-jsp</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/crud-with-java-jsp</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Object Oriented Thinking</title>
        <description>
          
          ###What are the main goals of the object-oriented programming?### 1. Abstraction, yes, i had to put this in the first place, in my point of view, this is the biggest goal of the OO programming 2. Encapsulation, which is a form of abstraction! 3. Reusability 4. Modularity 5. Readability Let’s...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/object-oriented-thinking</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/object-oriented-thinking</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Romantic Vision Of The Software Engineering</title>
        <description>
          
          Well, it all will start with your first steps on studying programming, a very innocent and and naive programming, i mean, your very first “Hello World” and the classics “Read 3 inputs and print the sum of them”, where your concerns will happen because of some missing commas, whitespaces and...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://digorithm.github.io/post/a-romantic-vision-of-the-software-engineering</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://digorithm.github.io/post/a-romantic-vision-of-the-software-engineering</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
