<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
        <channel>
                <title>Rodrigo Araujo's blog</title>
                <description>Few notes and thoughts on computer science, mathematics and technology</description>              
                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me</link>
                <atom:link href="http://rodrigoaraujo.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Web Scaling: Using Redis as Cache</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>Redis is such a great technology. Unfortunately, there's still people who don't know Redis or doesn't know that Redis can be used as Cache System to improve speed of responses.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/05/25/Web-Scaling:-Using-Redis-as-Cache/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/05/25/Web-Scaling:-Using-Redis-as-Cache/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Building your first Rest API with python</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>Are you total lost in this world full of jargons like API, Rest API, microservices and stuffs? Come here, sit, grab a cup of coffee, and let's talk briefly about it.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/04/22/Build-your-first-Rest-API-with-Python/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/04/22/Build-your-first-Rest-API-with-Python/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Using Python and AI to predict types of wine</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>&lt;html&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        I've been working with AI/Machine Learning at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jusbrasil.com.br/&quot;&gt;Jusbrasil&lt;/a&gt; recently, and it's being pretty challenging due to the &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of data that we have to deal with, so cleaning this data and making predictions and classifications in an acceptable time demands a nice AI architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
                That said I can say that I'm extremely thankful for a few technologies that are helping me go through this challenge &lt;em&gt;(and the pain of cleaning this amount of data)&lt;/em&gt;: Python, Scikit Learn, Pandas, and the whole stack that the Scikit Learn use, such as NumPy, SciPy, matplotlib and few others.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/03/31/using-python-and-AI-to-predict-types-of-wine/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/03/31/using-python-and-AI-to-predict-types-of-wine/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Making your machine think, learn and predict - Gradient Descent Algorithm in Java</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>The first thought I had when I started to study Design Patterns was “damn, is all this really necessary?&quot; I mean, so many patterns, so many details to do things that look simple to do without any further detailed thoughts. And I started to question myself if this was really a productive thing.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/01/09/Making-Your-Machine-Think-Learn-And-Predict--Gradient-Descent-Algorithm-in-Java/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/01/09/Making-Your-Machine-Think-Learn-And-Predict--Gradient-Descent-Algorithm-in-Java/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Why, how and where to Learn Design Patterns</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>The first thought I had when I started to study Design Patterns was “damn, is all this really necessary?&quot; I mean, so many patterns, so many details to do things that look simple to do without any further detailed thoughts. And I started to question myself if this was really a productive thing.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/01/06/Why-How-and-Where-To-Learn-Design-Patterns/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2015/01/06/Why-How-and-Where-To-Learn-Design-Patterns/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Thoughts on Automata Theory</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>I’ve been reading many texts on automata theory these times, and let me tell you, that’s such a wonderful thing. It pretty much explain how computers can…. compute! Simply put, Automata Theory deals with the logic of computation with respect to simple machines, referred to as Automata.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/10/31/Thoughts-on-Automata-Theory/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/10/31/Thoughts-on-Automata-Theory/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Fun with graphs pt1</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>Graph Theory is definitely one of my favorite branches of the Mathematics &amp; Computer Science, mostly because of its nearest infinity applications, in both real world problems and pure theoretical problems.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/10/10/Fun-with-graphs-pt1/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/10/10/Fun-with-graphs-pt1/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>CRUD with Java, JSP and MySQL</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>One of the most common kind of application in today's tech/business is the CRUD system, that is the idea of the user interacting with a database, so the user can Create, Retrieve, Update and Delete data from a database. Also, learning how to create a CRUD with a language is a great way to understand the basics of this language, the basics of software design, engineering and architecture.i</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/22/CRUD-with-Java,-JSP,-and-MySQL/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/22/CRUD-with-Java,-JSP,-and-MySQL/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Object Oriented Thinking</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>Let’s say that OO programming did never exist, so, i can say that any procedural programmer (C, fortran, cobol, etc..) who has a little notion about how to build organized codes, would, naturally, evolve to an organization that would look like the actual concept of OO programming.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/16/Object-Oriented-Thinking/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/16/Object-Oriented-Thinking/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>A Romantic Vision Of The Software Engineering</title>
                                        
                                
                                        <description>Well, it all will start with your first steps on studying programming, a very innocent and and naive programming, i mean, your very first “Hello World” and the classics “Read 3 inputs and print the sum of them”, where your concerns will happen because of some missing commas, whitespaces and some misplaced IF’s… things that at first sight may cause a little confusion, you’ll start to think that’s even something hard.</description>
                                
                                <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                                <link>http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/16/A-Romantic-Vision-Of-The-Software-Engineering/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodrigoaraujo.me/2014/07/16/A-Romantic-Vision-Of-The-Software-Engineering/</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>
